Department of Classical Studies Records UA145
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Department of Classical Studies Records
1857 -- 2000
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Department of Classics
UA145
26.14 Linear Feet 57 boxes
This collection contains the records of the Department of Classical Studies and includes subject files, photographs, and slides.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series: Department of Classics, Subject files and Photographs and slides.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records pertaining to the Department of Classical Studies at Tufts University including the course listings for Spring 2000, a portrait of professor Alpheus Augusts Keen, and both glass plate and 35 mm slides used in classes.
Biographical / Historical
In 1939, the Department of Greek and the Department of Latin united to form the Department of Classics. Its mission was to "discover the intrinsic worth of the culture of classic antiquity and to appreciate its pervasive relation to our own way of life." Undergraduates could pursue majors in Greek or Latin, and graduate students could undertake a Master of Arts in Classics.
The department offered rosters of courses in Greek and Latin that covered aspects of ancient Greek and Roman history, literature, and philosophy as well as language comprehension. There was also a Classical Studies track for which no knowledge of Greek or Latin was required. Its roster included courses in Greek and/or Roman literature, art, drama, pedagogy, and mythology. Prior to the creation of the Department of Classics, these topics had been taught under the headings of Classical Archaeology (1899-1911), Classical History and Archaeology (1911-1920), Classical Civilization (1920-1928), and as offerings of the Department of History (starting in 1932). The Greek and Latin professors continued to teach Greek and Roman history for the Department of History until 1952.
The curriculum of the Department of Classics remained fairly constant in the ensuing decades. Classics was one of six disciplines included in the doctoral program of Humanistic Studies, which was offered from 1959-1972. From 1961-1967, the department offered a study-abroad program based near Naples, Italy, in which students could do field work in classical archaeology and take courses in the history and literature of Greece and Rome.
By the 1970s, the description of Classics in the course catalogue had expanded to argue that "Classics is more than the study of the Greek and Latin languages; it can liberate the student from the parochialisms of both time and place." Classical Studies was touted as a liberal arts major, and a course on Women in Antiquity was added, perhaps reflecting an effort to be relevant to contemporary social concerns. In the 1990s, the catalogue description stressed that "the field of Classics is constantly changing in light of new discoveries, new methodologies, new interpretations and new relationships with other areas of study."
The most dramatic development within the Classics curriculum is the emergence of archaeology as a popular field of study. Courses about archaeology had been offered as far back as the 1890s. An undergraduate major in Classics and Archaeology was made available during the 1970s, and a Master of Arts in Classical Archaeology was established in 1981. However, the field came into its own when Archaeology gained the stature of interdisciplinary major (under the aegis of the Department of Classics) in 1984. The major incorporates courses from the arts, humanities, natural sciences and social sciences. The program is affiliated with summer field schools in Italy and France, and with Boston-area institutions including M.I.T.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Slides were transferred by the Department of Classical Studies in May 2022, UA-2022-060.
Curriculum and Instruction -- Academic Departments and Programs
- Department of Classics, subject files, 2000; UA145.001; 0.5 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the course listing for Spring 2000.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged as found.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Department of Classics, course listings Spring, 2000; UA145.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
- Photographs and slides, 1857 -- 1990s; UA145.002; 25.64 Linear Feet
  This series contains the portrait of Alpheus Augustus Keen, as well as 34 slide boxes of glass plate slides used in Classics classes. These glass sides are a mix of commercially produced materials and records of professors' travels. In addition, there are 21 slide boxes of modern 35 mm photographic slides, annotated, numbered, and indexed by subject. They were created and compiled by Professor Miriam Balmuth, who taught classics and archeology at Tufts for over 40 years starting in 1962. She was an expert in the coinage and trade routes of classical Sardinia, and these slides document her work in that area.
  - Portrait of professor Alpheus Augustus Keen, A. M., 1857; UA145.002.002.00001 (Box Shared 4)
    Accompanying this portrait is a plaque which reads "Alpheus Augustus Keen, A.M. 1824-1864. Professor of the ancient languages and literature in Tufts College. 1857-1864 Secretary of the faculty and librarian." This item was uncatalogued, framed, and wrapped on top of the Special Collection stacks. The art gallery determined that it was not part of their holdings. Note the location of the item, it is housed with other oversized items.
    paintings (visual works)
  - 35 mm slides - Maps and plans, Neolithic and Bronze Age Greece, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000006 (Box 2)
  - 35 mm slides - Maps and plans, Neolithic and Bronze Age Greece, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000007 (Box 3)
  - 35 mm slides - Maps and plans, Neolithic and Bronze Age Greece; Greek Architecture, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000008 (Box 4)
  - 35 mm slides - Greek Architecture, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000009 (Box 5)
  - 35 mm slides - Greek Architecture, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000010 (Box 6)
  - 35 mm slides - Greek Architecture; Greek Sculpture, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000011 (Box 7)
  - 35 mm slides - Greek Sculpture, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000012 (Box 8)
  - 35 mm slides - Greek Sculpture, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000013 (Box 9)
  - 35 mm slides - Greek Sculpture; Greek Vessels, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000014 (Box 10)
  - 35 mm slides - Greek Vessles, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000015 (Box 11)
  - 35 mm slides - Greek Vessles; Greek Coinage; Early Italic, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000016 (Box 12)
  - 35 mm slides - Early Italic; Roman Architecture, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000017 (Box 13)
  - 35 mm slides - Roman Architecture; Early Italic, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000018 (Box 14)
  - 35 mm slides - Early Italic; Etruscan Miscellaneous; Roman Architecture, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000019 (Box 15)
  - 35 mm slides - Roman Architecture, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000020 (Box 16)
  - 35 mm slides - Roman Architecture; Roman Sculpture & Relief, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000021 (Box 17)
  - 35 mm slides - Roman Sculpture & Relief; Roman Painting & Mosaic, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000022 (Box 18)
  - 35 mm slides - Roman Painting & Mosaic, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000023 (Box 19)
  - 35 mm slides - Roman Painting & Mosaic; Roman Coins; Miscellaneous, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000024 (Box 20)
  - 35 mm slides - Miscellaneous, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000025 (Box 21)
  - 35 mm slides - Miscellaneous, circa 1970s -- 1990s; UA145.000026 (Box 22)
  - Glass plate slides - L top unnumbered Egypt, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000027 (Box 23)
  - Glass plate slides - L00-70, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000028 (Box 24)
  - Glass plate slides - L71-152, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000029 (Box 25)
  - Glass plate slides - L153-234, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000030 (Box 26)
  - Glass plate slides - L235-315, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000031 (Box 27)
  - Glass plate slides - L316-393, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000032 (Box 28)
  - Glass plate slides - L394-471, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000033 (Box 29)
  - Glass plate slides - L472-553, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000034 (Box 30)
  - Glass plate slides - L554-632, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000035 (Box 31)
  - Glass plate slides - L633-734, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000036 (Box 32)
  - Glass plate slides - L735-841, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000037 (Box 33)
  - Glass plate slides - L842-994, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000038 (Box 34)
  - Glass plate slides - L995-1070, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000039 (Box 35)
  - Glass plate slides - L1071-1148, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000040 (Box 36)
  - Glass plate slides - L1149-1231, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000041 (Box 37)
  - Glass plate slides - L1232-1340, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000042 (Box 38)
  - Glass plate slides - R9-80, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000043 (Box 39)
  - Glass plate slides - R81-159, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000044 (Box 40)
  - Glass plate slides - R160-248, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000045 (Box 41)
  - Glass plate slides - R249-334, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000046 (Box 42)
  - Glass plate slides - R335-426, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000047 (Box 43)
  - Glass plate slides - R427-510, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000048 (Box 44)
  - Glass plate slides - R511-592, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000049 (Box 45)
  - Glass plate slides - R593-670, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000050 (Box 46)
  - Glass plate slides - R671-757, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000051 (Box 47)
  - Glass plate slides - R758-839, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000052 (Box 48)
  - Glass plate slides - R840-922, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000053 (Box 49)
  - Glass plate slides - R923-1007, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000054 (Box 50)
  - Glass plate slides - R1008-1085, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000055 (Box 51)
  - Glass plate slides - R1086-1154, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000056 (Box 52)
  - Glass plate slides - R1155-1233, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000057 (Box 53)
  - Glass plate slides - R1234-1325, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000058 (Box 54)
  - Glass plate slides - R1326-1390, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000059 (Box 55)
  - Glass plate slides - R1391-unnumbered, circa 1890 -- 1915; UA145.000060 (Box 56)